National Women's Health Network records SSC.MS.00360
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES IX. PROJECTS, PROGRAMS, AND REFORM EFFORTS, 1963-2007
  The International and export to third world countries section contains articles, clippings, and printed materials from the Agency for International Development, the Asian Regional Workshop on Injectable Contraceptives; and correspondence, articles and correspondence on Depo-Provera in Australia, New Zealand, Canada, England, India, Jamaica and the West Indies, Kenya, the Philippines, Thailand, and Zimbabwe. It also includes a printed transcript, statements and reports from hearings before the House Subcommittee on International Economic Policy and Trade. In addition there are materials related to the Federal Policy on Export of Banned Substances, the Interagency Working Group on a Hazardous Substances Export Policy, International Planned Parenthood Federation's endorsement of Depo-Provera and the National Alliance of Third World Journalists. Finally there is a student authored paper. "The Shot Heard Round the World;" testimony before the House Committee on Interior and insular Affairs by Norma Swenson, correspondence with the Word Bank; and a report by the World Health Organization.
  The media and outreach section contains articles and clippings and other materiasl related to a documentary film, "The Ultimate Test Animal" produced by Karen Branan and Bill Turnley. The NWHN media campaign consists of a Depo-Provera information packet, press releases, news alerts, radio announcements and statements, press conferences and kit, lists of media contacts, and The Depo-Provera Debates: A Report by the National Women Health Network. In addition there is a talk by Judith Rooks and a satiric skit: "The Moral Majority Salutes International Women's Day."
  The Organization section contains correspondence, agendas and printed materials on Consumer Exchange meetings, the California Institute of Medical Ethics, the Coalition to Stop Depo-Provera, Institute for the Study of Medical Ethics, and miscellaneous women's health groups. There are Depo-Provera petitions, pro-Depo-Provera material, and a NWHN request for funding.
  Because of the names and personal information contained in the Registry section most of it is closed until 2060. Only the statistical analysis of the results and worksheets is open. The closed portions consist of lists of client information, correspondence in response to the Network's questionnaires and completed questionnaires. Finally there is material related to the Select Committee on Population; the National Science Foundation's "Toxic Substances: Decisions and Values"; and NWHN work plans, notes, and chronology of the Depo-Provera Project.
  DES is the ninth subseries. DES (Diethylstilbestrol) is a synthetic form of estrogen prescribed to pregnant women between 1938 and 1971 to prevent miscarriage which has been linked to vaginal and cervical cancer in young women whose mothers took the drug during pregnancy. DES was also used as a "morning after pill" at college campuses and hospital emergency rooms, although not approved by the FDA for this purpose. In 1980 the Network warned the FDA regarding the use of DES and continued to lobby against the dangers of DES. There is a report from the FDA on the illegal use of DES in animal (cattle) feed and a bibliography of sources on DES. In 2001, in partnership with the Centers of Disease Control and Prevention, the NWHN participated in a DES evaluation survey sent to random NWHN members to ascertain health related information especially related to DES. Correspondence with the CDC and WESTAT, the research corporation that was used to conduct the survey as well as copies of the survey are included in this subseries as well as a folder of miscellaneous correspondence. The subseries also includes correspondence and reports with the DES daughters Identification Project of Massachusetts and information about its affiliation with the Network and it's class action suit Payton et al v. Abbott Labs. There is also material related DES granddaughters and a court case regarding the cross generation effects of DES. In another survey (DES: Self Assessment) conducted in cooperation with the CDC, the Network sent an assessment questionnaire to its members. Included in this section is the survey along with related correspondence and plans. A DES Task Force was formed as a result of pressure by the NWHN. There is a summary report included here. Under the section Legal Issues there are articles and clippings, court transcripts, clippings, correspondence and printed materials related to the Joyce Bichler v. Eli Lilly case and additional information on the class action suit Payton et al. v. Abbott Labs. Finally there are statements and testimonies before Congress by some NWHN representatives and miscellaneous legal correspondence and printed materials. The meetings section contains agendas, minutes, and correspondence on meetings of Obstetrics and Gynecology Advisory Committee of the FDA, the Centers for Disease Control, the National Institutes of Health, and Consumer Exchange. NWHN press releases and statements were aimed at educating the public regarding the dangers of DES. The Organizations sections contains pamphlets, printed materials and correspondence regarding DES Action and DES National Education Campaign Working Group. Finally there are materials and articles on DES research, and a folder of DES related transcripts and testimonies.
  The tenth subseries is Endorsements. The Network staff labeled these files "endorsements" and they contain letters and miscellaneous material regarding the NWHN endorsements for various causes, products, persons, conferences, and organizations. There is a separate folder on the Network's support of Henry Foster for Surgeon General. The rest of the subseries is arranged chronologically.
  In 1998 the NWHN, in cooperation with the Epilepsy Foundation's Women's Initiative, made a commitment to raise awareness of the issues around epilepsy and women's health. The eleventh subseries, Epilepsy Outreach Project, contains correspondence, project plans, mailing lists, and printed materials about this collaboration.
  The NWHN has played a central role in empowering women to make informed choices about their reproductive health and supported federally mandated, written informed consent for contraceptives, especially long-acting contraceptives. The twelfth subseries, Informed consent, contains correspondence, printed materials, reports, and survey results regarding this effort. In 1983 the Network requested copies of contraceptive consent forms used by college health services. The section on the College Health Services Survey contains correspondence, model consent forms and information sheets, and responses to the survey. This is followed by general correspondence on informed consent; appendices to a Report on the Public Forum on Informed Consent in Clinical Research conducted in Emergency Circumstances published by the FDA; and a statement by the NWHN, "Written Informed Consent and Long-Acting Contraception: Disincentive to Coercion."
  The thirteenth Subseries, Insurance reform, contains articles, correspondence, and printed materials. As part of the Insurance Reform Working Group, the NWHN was involved in liability insurance, medical malpractice insurance, and the repeal of the McCarran-Ferguson Act that exempted the insurance business from most federal regulation. There are also folders on the Network's work for medical malpractice insurance, national health insurance, and against sex discrimination in health and disability insurance.
  The NWHN's program for improving the health care of lesbians reflects its vision of a health care system for all. The fourteenth subseries, Lesbian health, contains information collected for an educational packet sent out by the Network on lesbian health issues. There is a copy of "Lesbian Health Issues and Recommendations" distributed by the National Gay and Lesbian Taskforce, and an endorsement of the Whitman/Weller Clinic's lesbian health agenda.
  In response to the many calls and letters from women who believed that they received improper, inadequate, or faulty health care, the Network's Litigation Information Service provides attorney consultations and referral services to individuals who contact the Network seeking legal representation. This subseries consists primarily of correspondence sent to the Service regarding Benedictin, the Dalkon Shield, Depo-Provera, DES, medical records, and Tampax and toxic shock syndrome. In addition there is correspondence regarding legal issues of the Service as well as office procedures.
  The Network's Mental Health subseries contains correspondence and printed materials regarding its stance against electroconvulsive therapy; and a description of a project on the mental health of mothers who were involved in custody battles for their children; and correspondence, reports and notes on the labeling of PMS as a mental illness.
  The seventeenth subseries is the M idlife and Older Women's Project. This project addressed the problems of aging women by empowering them to take responsibility for the wellness of their bodies. The goals of the project were to establish self-help groups, expand the knowledge base about midlife and older women's health, and advocate for improvements in health care delivery. It consists of budget and project information, notes, articles, reports, and printed material on caring for the aged and long term care. Agendas, reports, and printed materials of the House Select Committee on Aging and meeting material from the National Coalition on Older Women's Issues are also found here. The Network worked with Citizens for the Improvement of Nursing Homes and the National Citizens Coalition for Nursing Home Reform generating correspondence, reports, meeting and printed materiasl from these two organizations. The Network also supported the Georgia Nursing Home Legislation and a text of the legislation is included. There are also Included as well are publications from the Older Women's League; correspondence and printed materials of the Pepper Commission regarding health access and long term care; and statements, reports and notes on the Senate Subcommittee on Aging. Finally there are agendas, reports, and printed materials on three conferences: The Older Woman: Continuities and Discontinuities, White House Conference on Aging, and White House Mini Conference on Older Women.
  In 1983 President Reagan's proposed budget drastically cut nursing education funds. The NWHN spearheaded a campaign to support these appropriations for nursing education. The Nursing education funding legislation subseries contains correspondence, fact sheets, printed materials and news alerts regarding this campaign.
  There is one file of correspondence, notes, printed materials, and reports in the nineteenth subseries, Occupational health and safety, about glutaraldyde poisoning in health care workers.
  The NWHN advocates regular pap tests as an early detection for cervical cancer. The twentieth subseries, Pap tests, contains correspondence, printed materials, reports, and notes regarding pap tests, and companies that produce clinical products for testing and new test technology.
  The NWHN has taken a stand against risks to women and unborn children and affirms that every woman has the right to control her childbirth experiences including the type of care during pregnancy and the circumstances of the birth. The twenty-first subseries, Pregnancy and Childbirth, contains correspondence, reports, testimonies, a position paper, and printed materials. The drug bendectin, prescribed to pregnant women to treat morning sickness, was introduced in 1956 and removed from the market in 1983 because it caused birth defects. The Network created a registry for women who had taken the drug. There are several responses to the registry inquiry. The organization also collected data on Cesareans and episiotomies and found that the rate of cesareans had risen and that episiotomies were largely unnecessary. Correspondence, reports, printed and statistical material document this issue. There is a copy of a Network position paper on maternal health and childbirth. Finally there are NWHN testimonies and position papers on bendectin, fetal monitoring, induction of labor, and preterm labor.
  In 1988 the Network sent a questionnaire on women's health to the presidential candidates. This twenty-second subseries, Presidential Candidates, contain answers to the questionnaire from George W. Bush, Al Gore, Bob Dole, Jesse Jackson, and Pete du Pont.
  The NWHN supports access to safe and effective reproductive technologies including a woman's right to abortion care and contraception. The twenty-third subseries, Reproductive Rights, contains four sections: abortion, Campaign To Stop Anti-fertility Vaccines, contraception, and C.R.A.C.K. (Children Requiring a Caring Community).
  In 1986 the Center for Population Options requested help from the Network to gather information on anti-choice activities targeting teenagers. A file on abortion choice and teenagers contains a copy of a survey sent out to pro-choice organizations. In 1985 the NWHN conducted a study of Washington D.C. area non-hospital abortion clinics with the intention of producing a resource guide. A file about the study contains the project description, protocol and questionnaire.
  There are notes for a conference, Abortion in the Era of States Rights, sponsored by the Network (although it is not clear if the conference ever happened) and agendas and reports from meetings of the Abortion Information Exchange.
  Along with many other organizations, the NWHN was on the steering committee for the Abortion Rights Action Week in October 1979. This file contains correspondence and memoranda, organization manuals, mailing lists, printed materials, meeting agendas, and notes related to this event. There is a small file on the Abortion Speak Out in celebration of the 20th anniversary of the Redstockings which provides an important insight into the pro choice movement. A file of statements, witness lists, agenda, reports, and printed materials from hearings of the House Judiciary Subcommittee on Civil and Constitutional Rights documents abortion clinic violence.
  Fake abortion clinics funded by anti-abortion groups advertised as legitimate abortion and birth control clinics. Women seeking services from them were then shown anti-abortion films with false and misleading information. The Network's Fake Clinic Project denounced the existence of these clinics and launched a nationwide campaign against them. This file includes background information on, and brochures from, fake clinics, and a PPFA generated packet on their Expose "Fake Clinic" Campaign as well as unidentified notes regarding fake clinics in relation to the TV program "Geraldo." There is a file of NWHN-generated press releases and miscellaneous material on the Fake Clinic Project. Some of this material was created for distribution in Network packets and there is a folder of responses to the project packet. Finally there are files of correspondence and printed materials related to the Network's campaign focused on getting the Yellow Pages to list abortion services separately from abortion alternatives.
  The remainder of the abortion section contains clinic lists and printed materials on Federal funding of anti-abortion clinics; press releases, printed materials, statements and testimonies related to the anti-abortion Hatch Amendment; correspondence, printed materials, organizational instructions on three events in which the NWHN was involved; and correspondence, printed materials, and reports on menstrual extraction as an early method to terminate a pregnancy and on eleven abortion related organizations. Finally there are documents related to the public relations aspects of the campaign: press releases and position papers, Roe v. Wade 13th anniversary, NARAL's Silent No More Campaign, and the campaign against the anti-abortion film "Silent Scream".
  The NWHN was involved in a campaign to stop the use of anti-fertility vaccines, especially international use of vaccines to control fertility. The section on the Campaign to Stop Anti-Fertility Vaccines consists of correspondence, printed materials, reports, and notes on the Network's involvement.
  The contraception section contains "Contraceptive Research Priorities" by Judy Norsigian and critiques of contraceptive research by the Network. It also includes historical information on emergency contraception, testimony by Belita Cowan before the FDA on the Morning after Pill, as well as miscellaneous correspondence, printed materials, reports and notes. The NWHN backed the approval of a new contraceptive technology, Lea's Shield and generated correspondence, printed materials, notes, meeting agendas, testimony, and policy briefings on this barrier method of contraception. In 1983 the Network launched a petition drive to oust Deputy Assistant Secretary For Population Affairs Marjorie Mecklenburg as because she was the author of parental notification regulation requiring family organizations to notify parents when their teenage daughters received prescription birth control. Correspondence, lists, and printed materials document the Mecklenburg petition. Finally, correspondence, notes, reports, guidelines and printed materials on Norplant and oral contraceptives are included here.
  The final section in the Reproductive rights subseries contains correspondence, printed materials, reports, and notes, on the Network's campaign against the C.R.A.C.K program which offered monetary incentives to drug and alcohol abusers to participate in long term or permanent birth control.
  The twenty-fourth subseries, Sterilization abuse, relates to the Network's project to bring together major women's health groups in New York City working on sterilization abuse, to assist them to monitor NYC's municipal hospitals. It contains an abstract of the project; correspondence; a press release by the Network; completed questionnaires; mailing lists from a survey of sterilization practices; and miscellaneous correspondence, printed materials, and notes.
  In 2001 the Network surveyed young women about their most import health issue. The twenty-fifth subseries, Survey of Young Women, contains returned questionnaires, survey results, and correspondence.
  In 1980 epidemiologists reported the appearance of toxic shock syndrome (TSS) which correlated with a superabsorbent tampons, Rely, introduced in 1978 by Procter and Gamble. The Toxic Shock Syndrome Task Force was created to investigate the epidemic as the number of reported cases increased. The CDC reported that users of Rely were at increased risk for developing TSS and Procter and Gamble recalled the product. The NWHN advocated adequate pre-market testing of tampons, proper labeling for tampon ingredients and absorbency, and presented testimony at FDA hearings. The twenty-sixth subseries, Tampons and toxic shock syndrome, reflects this campaign. It contains printed materials correspondence, and notes regarding absorbency and tampon labeling; and general correspondence on TSS, including letters requesting TSS/tampon information. It also includes correspondence, testimonies and statements, reports, and meeting materials related to the Network's relationship to the FDA and tampons. The Network requested a list of tampon ingredients from suppliers and there is a folder of replies from tampon manufacturers. The Network produced a packet of information on TSS, and a related report is included her, as well as press releases, and miscellaneous printed material. There are eight files of reports, meeting materials, participants, correspondence, and notes from the Tampons Task Force, followed by correspondence, printed materials, and Network position papers on contraceptive sponges as an alternative to tampons. In 1984 the FDA's Division of Consumer Affairs had a pilot program to education teenagers about TSS. The "Toxic Shock Syndrome and Tampons Pilot Education Program Evaluation" assesses this program. Finally there is a folder of miscellaneous printed materials and notes.
  The Title X Family Planning Program was enacted in 1970 to provide comprehensive family planning and other preventive health services to low income or uninsured people who might not otherwise have access to these health care services. The Network supported this program and pressured the government to continue funding when it was threatened. Included in this twenty-seventh subseries, Title X, are notes, correspondence, and printed materials on program regulations; correspondence related to school based clinics (Title X and Senate 881); correspondence and meeting materials from the Title X Coalition; and miscellaneous material including letters to Congress and the Administration.
  Weight discrimination advocacy, the twenty-eighth subseries, contains printed materials, correspondence, and meeting agendas which relate to healthy weight, medical treatment of obesity, weight discrimination, and fitness.
  The NWHN was one of the first national organizations to alert women to their risk of AIDS. In 1988 the Network proposed a comprehensive study of women specifically related to HIV prevention. This included making AIDS information accessible, creating a forum for women at risk, advocating for prevention methods, and organizing a comprehensive survey of health agencies, the ultimate goal of which was to enable the Network and other organizations to make policy recommendations to better meet prevention needs. The twenty-ninth subseries, Women and AIDS Project, consists of material related to several aspects of this project. The Women and Aids Advocacy Project was aimed at minority women in high risk communities and its goal was to "integrate women's needs into public policy." The first section describes this project.
  In 1987 the Network developed an AIDS Education Activity Workshop to reach college age women by using games, contests, skits, and questionnaires. Correspondence, descriptions, notes, evaluations, and printed materials document the workshop. There are notes and forms for a possible registry of women with HIV. In 1991 the Network helped sponsor Women's Voices: Speaking AIDS. There are proposals, correspondence and a report from this conference, along with a folder of notes and printed materials related to miscellaneous AIDS conferences with which NWHN was associated. In 1997 Mia Luluquisen produced a report on the epidemiology of AIDS and this report is included along with a literature review. Files of correspondence, printed materials, agendas, and reports from eight AIDS organizations with which the Network was in cooperation or affiliated with are also found here. Included in the publications reports and statements section is promotion for Chris Norwood's Advice for Life: a Woman's guide to AIDS Risks and Prevention; correspondence and printed materials related to the Network's brochure "AIDS What Every Woman Needs to Know;" and miscellaneous reports and public statements among them the final report of the Women and AIDs Project. There is also a file containing notes and ideas for a seminar on AIDS.